Gest, Howard mss., 1941-2011 LMC 2573
Lilly Library
Gest, Howard mss.
1941-2011
2007, 2008, 2011
Lilly Library
Gest, Howard
LMC 2573
3 Boxes 3 standard
The Gest, Howard mss., ca. 1941-2011, consist of the correspondence, papers, reprints and copies of the work of Prof. Howard Gest, Distinguished Professor Emeritus of the Indiana University Department of Microbiology.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Professor Gest was born in London, England and emigrated with his family to the US when he was one year old. During undergraduate studies at UCLA (B.A., 1942) he spent two summers assisting Max Delbruck and Salvador Luria doing research on bacterial viruses at the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory (New York). In 1942, Gest began graduate work with Delbruck at Vanderbilt University, but World War II interrupted his studies. He accepted a position on the Manhattan Atomic Bomb Project with the eminent physical chemist Charles Coryell. Their research focuses on characterization of the radioactive elements formed in uranium fission. After World War II ended, Gest completed graduate work (Ph.D. 1949) at Washington University (St. Louis) as the first student of Martin Kamen, a pioneer nuclear chemist renowned as the co-discoverer of carbon 14. During this period, Gest also did research with Alfred Hershey on the fate of radioactive phosphorus during the multiplication of bacterial viruses. The latter culminated in the discovery of "P-32 suicide" of bacteriophage. Prior to 1950, Gest had worked with Delbruck, Luria and Hershey, who shared a Nobel Prize in 1969. Gest has been on the faculties of Case Western Reserve University and Washington University. He has been a visiting researcher at the California Institute of Technology, Dartmouth Medical School, Stanford University, Oxford University, Tokyo University, and UCLA. Professor Gest has been a Guggenheim Fellow twice and has served on a number of advisory committees of the US Government. He is widely recognized for his research on microbial physiology and metabolism, especially with photosynthetic bacteria. Gest is a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Society for Microbiology, American Academy of Microbiology, and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into the following series: I. The Manhattan Project, II. Astrobiology, III. Microbiology, IV. Publications, V. Profiles of Scientists, VI. Correspondence, and VII. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Content Note
The Manhattan Project includes all collected materials relating to the Manhattan Project and is organized into the following sub-series: A. Szilard Petition, B. Periodicals, C. Book Extracts, D. Articles, E. Correspondence, and F. Miscellaneous. Astrobiology includes collected materials around the creation of astrobiology as a field and especially the search for extraterrestrial life; it is divided into the following sub-series: A. Extraterrestrial life, B. Mars, C. NASA, and D. Miscellaneous. Microbiology includes collected materials in Gest's field of specialty. Publications includes Gest's own publications about various topics in microbiology and biochemistry. Profiles of scientists consists of Gest's experiment in profiling/collecting biographies of various scientists he knew or worked with. Correspondence includes Gest's correspondence to other scientists and correspondence about various publications. Miscellaneous includes other scientific materials and audio-visual materials.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2007, 2008, 2011
Science; biochemistry; Exobiology; Nuclear warfare and history; Extraterrestrial beings
- I. THE MANHATTAN PROJECT
  - The Szilard Petition
    - Copies of petition and lists of signers (Box 1)
    - "Memoir by a Signer" (Box 1)
    - "What Might Have Been: The Ill-Fated Szilard Petition" (Box 1)
    - "An Ill-Fated Petition" - Original (Box 1)
    - "An Ill-Fated Petition" 4 copies (Box 1)
    - "The Bomb Scientists' Ill Fated Petition" (Box 1)
    - "Secret File 76: A Personal Perspective", 9 Sept. 1994 (Box 1)
    - "The Ill-Fated Szilard Petition" (Box 1)
    - "Secret File 76" (Box 1)
    - "The Secret Atomic Bomb Petition", 2001 (Box 1)
    - "Scientists Send an Ill-Fated Petition" (Box 1)
  - Periodicals
    - TIME, 20 Aug. 1945 (Box 1)
    - One World or None, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists XX.8, Oct. 1964 (Box 1)
    - Review 9.4, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists 40th Anniversary Issue, Aug. 1985 (Box 1)
    - Technology Review, Aug.-Sept. 1990 (Box 1)
    - F.A.S. Public Interest Report 43.7, 1990 (Box 1)
    - New Scientist, 15 Dec. 1990 (Box 1)
    - The Defense Monitor XIX.7, 1990 (Box 1)
    - American Heritage of Invention and Technology, 1991 (Box 1)
    - F.A.S. Public Interest Report 47.4, July-Aug. 1994 (Box 1)
    - The Washington Post, 26 Sept. 1994 (Box 1)
    - U.S. News, 31 July 1995 (Box 1)
  - Book extracts
    - Atomic Quest - Arthur Holly Compton, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Brighter than a Thousand Suns - Robert Jungk, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Now It Can be Told - Leslie R. Grove, 1962 (Box 1)
    - The Atomic Age - Morton Grodzins, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Mission with LeMay - Curtis E. LeMay with MacKinlay Kantor, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Scientists in Politics - Donald A. Strickland, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Lawrence and Oppenheimer - Nuel Pharr Davis, 1968 (Box 1)
    - A World Destroyed - Martin J. Sherwin, 1975 (Box 1)
    - J. Robert Oppenheimer: Shatterer of Worlds - Peter Goodchild, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Day One - Peter Wyden, 1984 (Box 1)
    - H.G. Wells: Aspects of a Life - Anthony West, 1984 (Box 1)
    - The Making of the Atomic Bomb - Richard Rhodes, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Iron Eagle - Thomas M. Coffrey, 1986 (Box 1)
    - The Road to Trinity - K.D. Nichols, 1987 (Box 1)
    - The Recollection of Eugene P. Wigner - Andrew Szanton, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Operation Epsilon - Charles Frank, 1993 (Box 1)
    - The Catcher Was a Spy - David Dawidoff, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Hitler's Uranium Club - Jeremy Bernstein, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Los Alamos - Joseph Kanon, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Copenhagen, Act II -Michael Frayn, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - Newspaper/magazine extracts I (Box 1)
    - Newspaper/magazine extracts II (Box 1)
    - "Nuclear Wizard" - Lord Zuckerman (Box 1)
    - "Einstein the Inventor" - Thomas P. Hughes, 1991 (Box 1)
    - "Of Physics, Friendship, and the Atomic Bomb" - James Glanz, 31 July 2000 (Box 1)
    - "Mass Distributions for Monoenergetic-Neutron-Induced Fission of ²³⁵U" (Box 1)
    - "The Elusive Dr. Szilard" - Alice Kimball Smith, July 1960 (Box 1)
    - "Behind the Decision to Use the Atomic Bomb" - Alice Kimball Smith, Sept. 1958 (Box 1)
    - "An Analysis of 'Two Culture'" - Barton J. Bernstein, 1990 (Box 1)
    - "A Few Words about This Picture" - Stanley Goldberg, 1991 (Box 1)
    - "Science and Politics" - Margaret Gowing, May 1977 (Box 1)
    - "Leo Szilard: Scientist, Activist, Visionary", 1985 (Box 1)
    - Various in Historical Studies in the Physical and Biological Sciences 18.2, 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Annals of Government: Serving the President", 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Birth of the Bomb" - Paul Bracken, 17 Sept. 1984 (Box 1)
    - Various (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995-2002 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Part I (Box 1)
    - Part II (Box 1)
    - Part III (Box 1)
- II. ASTROBIOLOGY
  - Extraterrestrial Life
    - Cartoon - Kallaugher (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings I (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings II (Box 2)
    - "Life on Mars?" - Smithsonian, May 2005 (Box 2)
    - "Life-Form in Meteorites" - Harold Urey, 24 mar. 1964 (Box 2)
    - "Martian Microbes?" - Bruce Murray, 1989 (Box 2)
    - "Exploring for a Record of Ancient Martian Life", 24 Nov. 1995 (Box 2)
    - "Pale Blue Dot 2 Workshop", May 2000 (Box 2)
    - Various documents (Box 2)
  - Mars
    - Articles (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
    - 'Mars Meteorite Compendium", 1996 (Box 2)
    - "Point Clear Exobiology Instrumentation Workshop", 13-17 May 1996 (Box 2)
    - "Meteorite Working Group I" (Box 2)
    - "Meteorite Working Group II" (Box 2)
    - "Meteorite Working Group III" (Box 2)
  - NASA
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
    - Various Documents (Box 2)
    - TIME Press Conference, 1996 (Box 2)
    - International Journal of Astrobiology I, Jan 2002 (Box 2)
    - "Congressional Earmark for Higher Education 1990-2003" (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Introduction to USRA (Box 2)
    - Research and Creative Activity: Space (Box 2)
    - Various Publications (Box 2)
- III. MICROBIOLOGY
  - Origin of Life
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
    - Publications Part I (Box 2)
    - Publications Part II (Box 2)
    - "Earliest Organic Evolution" (Box 2)
    - "The Origin of Life" - Haldane (Box 2)
    - "Organic Matter in Meteorites and Precambrian Rocks" (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - "Different Forms of Microbial Manganese Oxidation and Reduction" (Box 2)
  - "Solar Lake as a Model for a Modern Oil Producing Environment" (Box 2)
  - Microbiology Today 27, Feb. 2000 (Box 2)
  - "The Chemosynthetic Support of Life and the Microbial Diversity at Deep-Sea Hydrothermal Vents" (Box 2)
  - "Archean Microfossils and Microfossil-like Objects", Jan. 1980 (Box 2)
  - "Life at High Temperatures" - Thomas D. Brock (Box 2)
  - "Oases at the Bottom of the Ocean" (Box 2)
  - Short articles (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- IV. PUBLICATIONS
  - "The Focus on Microbes" - Drafts (Box 2)
  - "The 2006 Astrobiology Follies Return of the Phantom Martian Microbes" (Box 2)
  - "A Major Contribution to Modern Molecular Biology" (Box 2)
  - "Microbes in the Search for Extraterrestrial Life" (Box 2)
  - "Reflections on Extraterrestrial Life and 'Astrobiology'", Aug. 2005 (Box 2)
  - "Phantasms of 'Astrobiology' and the Importance of Definitions" (Box 2)
  - "A Microbiologist's Odyssey" - Photosynthesis Research 40.2, May 1994 (Box 2)
  - Articles in Photosynthesis Research Photosynthesis Research (Box 2)
  - Articles in The International Union of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (Box 2)
  - Articles in Perspectives in Biology and Medicines (Box 2)
  - Articles in FEMS Microbiology Letters (Box 2)
  - Various (Box 2)
  - "Retrospections on a Career" - Spiral notebook (Box 2)
  - "An Experiment in Scientific Biography" - Spiral notebook (Box 2)
  - "A Panorama of the Emergence of Modern Microbiology" - Spiral notebook (Box 2)
  - Associations with Outstanding Scientists - Spiral notebook, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Associations with Outstanding Scientists - Spiral notebook, amended by Donald Gray, 2008 (Box 2)
- V. PROFILES OF SCIENTISTS
  - Howard Gest (Box 3)
  - Hudson Freeze (Box 3)
  - Martin Kamen (Box 3)
  - Norman Horowitz (Box 3)
  - Robert Hill (Box 3)
  - Robert Hill - Fotosintesi (Box 3)
  - Max Delbrück (Box 3)
  - Max Delbrück - Problems in Modern Biology (Box 3)
  - James Barber (Box 3)
  - Paul Berg (Box 3)
  - Melvin Calvin (Box 3)
  - Charles Coryell (Box 3)
  - Charles Coryell An Introduction to Nuclear Chemistry (Box 3)
  - Hans Krebs (Box 3)
  - Charles Yanofsky (Box 3)
  - Cornelius B. Van Niel (Box 3)
  - Harland Wood (Box 3)
  - Peter Mitchell (Box 3)
  - Rita Levi-Montalcini (Box 3)
  - Fritz Lipmann (Box 3)
  - Niels Bohr (Box 3)
  - Samuel Goldsmit (Box 3)
  - Leo Szilard (Box 3)
  - Leo Szilard - "Leo Szilard: His Version of the Facts" (Box 3)
  - Leo Szilard - "Reminiscences" (Box 3)
  - Leo Szilard The Humanist, May-June 1960 (Box 3)
- VI. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Martin Kamen
    - From Gest Part I, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
    - From Gest Part II, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
    - From Gest Part III, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
    - To Gest Part I, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
    - To Gest Part II, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
    - To Gest Part III, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
    - To Gest Part IV, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
  - Robert Hill, 1965-1989 (Box 3)
  - Max Delbrück, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Joel Mandelstam, 1966-1983 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- VII. MISCELLANEOUS
  - Handwritten notes (Box 3)
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 3)
  - Science and Culture (Box 3)
  - Biochemistry (Box 3)
  - Chemistry in Britain (Box 3)
  - "Initial Studies of YFI" - Composition Notebook (Box 3)
  - Various Documents Part I (Box 3)
  - Various Documents Part II (Box 3)
  - Interview with Howard Gest - DVD (Box 3)
  - Lecture - Audiocassette (Box 3)
  - Delbruck Lecture - Audio Reel (Box 3)
  - Howard Gest Guide - CD ROM (Box 3)